welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
you
okay thank you for technology playground
with Bonita Roy at the stoah dialogue
around what matters most at the knife
edge so I just gonna jump in not because
your introduction wasn't good but
because there's like seems like there's
feedback on your mic or something
[Music]
alright other people hearing it too like
maybe gonna yes other people are hearing
it as well is that better yes that's
much better
okay microphone setting was off okay um
well that was probably the case in this
conference I was just on and nobody
complains did be like okay so welcome to
the psycho technology playground with
Bonita Roy at the stall of the store as
a place to me in dialogue around what
matters most at the knife edge of
history and you are here on the knife
edge okay so I started I was thinking
through this morning about like what is
the sake of Technology playground and so
I wanted to try to dive a little deeper
into that territory you know we got
started by doing those source code
protocols that was a little more like
cognitive and conceptual but can we dive
in from there going to kind of a deeper
regions of mind this is always a
challenge because I'm kind of making
kind of revising what I do in the
research the insight Center here for
kind of a short zoom application so
there's always a very experimental
aspect to it and I think that the other
sessions have been lovely and your
participation has been great so now I'm
going to try to take on a
another challenge so we're gonna do a
fuse a series about unpacking the nature
of the experience and you know some of
you have probably have done a lot of
work in meditation you may belong to a
tradition so I don't mean to undermine
the more sophisticated work you're doing
but what I'm trying intending to do is
to see if we can accelerate a shared
understanding of some of these
sophisticated wisdom skills so in many
traditions I'm thinking here of modern
meditation trainers like shins and young
Daniel Ingram Kenneth Falk somebody you
might you might know some of these words
they they create a labeling system
that's gonna sound jus allistic the
point is to start as if these are
separate things just so we can parse the
territory but eventually we reclaim them
and we integrate them so Kenneth oak for
example will say everything is either
experience or thought ok so we're just
going to use this framework I know it
sounds hopelessly dualistic but it does
come from these traditions and what we
want to do is see how accurately and
precisely we can talk about them in a
shared language that's not hopelessly
confounded by all these spiritual terms
and these split hairs in these nuances
and Buddha scholastics and cognitive
neuroscience ok so this is part of a
modern minimalist approach to unpacking
the nature of the experience so we're
just going to have these two
placeholders they should work as
placeholders for now we have thought and
we have experience and today we're just
going to work with thought and we're
going to work with the most ordinary and
in some sense irritating or distracting
mode of thought and that's called
inner talk or inner speech right it's
when we are going on an interview and we
rehearse
you know we rehearse what we're going to
say we have the whole conversation
oh no no then you rehearse it and you
rehearse and rehearse it's the inner
speech is any kind of thought that
actually is like virtualized talk so
before we go on just any everybody get
it does everybody grok what we're
talking about what kind of extraordinary
human experience we're talking about ok
now imagine you met
you're space traveler and you met a
intelligent species that could speak to
you but maybe you have transponders so
you can you can speak but they don't
have inner talk okay the the two
placeholders are thought in experience
and today we're looking only at stock
that was a question from the chat and
the part of thought we're looking at is
just this thing called inner talk okay
so we're gonna start examining than this
okay so you meet an alien and they talk
to each other like they make sounds in
their air and but they never they have
they don't have inner talk and the alien
says what is that how would you explain
what is happening when you have inner
talk so the alien might say do you mean
you hear something and you would have to
hedge well I don't actually hear it like
I'm hearing you now so this is what I'm
asking you what is what is actually
happening I mean this is so familiar to
you right it's like the most ordinary
thing and actually sometimes it's like
when you have a song in your in your
head it's very similar right you hear a
song in your head and the aliens like
what do you mean you hear a song in your
head like - you hearin well if you
actually heard it that would be either
real perception or aural hallucination
but we're talking about this other thing
that seems to be enclosed in your
thought so what kinds of things would
you say yeah so someone said imagining
it but then you have to describe what is
imagination so what is this thing that
is happening when you're doing this I
mean you're thinking of recipes you're
thinking you make lists in your head
you've got like schedules and then you
no but if you god forbid you're planning
a wedding a lot of that is going on in
your head what is that it isn't it
strange that we don't know what that is
so yeah someone says okay this is good
someone's are splitting into two persons
one talking to another talking to
oneself but how does the talking happen
do you move your mouth do you make
sounds so this is a good first move you
understand there's a split perspective
of a listener and a talker
all right so you've kind of created a
spatial George Herbert Mead made this
point that you're actually playing two
roles okay so when you're listening to
the talk in your head which which one
are you the talker or the listener or
can you do you toggle back and forth so
that's one part of it this ability to
this ability to hold both perspectives
while this inner talk is happening but
how does inner talk happen there's a
thought that comes from a lot
neurological pathway okay
yes that that is one way to start
getting at it is that neurological
pathway intentional then for example how
do you own how do you how do you take
over the intentionality of thinking out
things previous burn previously burned
by past experience Tonya's saying this
yes what's this notion of previously
burned
don't feel split if I'm aware of it in a
way that feels separate there's also a
way to be aware of it okay yes so
there's so that there is you can be
completely unaware of the neuro
pathological processing of thought or we
you can be constant you can have both
perspectives and you could be like
sometimes if I'm writing something I'm
too lazy to get out of bed I actually
start well maybe the title should be
this you know I'm actually very
intentionally manipulating the symbol
symbolic words in my head so this notion
of how what identity you are how many
identities is very important so how does
it okay yes so this notion of burning
like burning a CD right is very it's
very good now how does where does the
burning come from you're going to get
into an infinite regress if you say it
comes from earlier thoughts right what
is that which burns attention emotion
yes but how does that's true if you're
recreating emotion but I'm we're talking
about inner talk the words the speaker
in your head
ah okay who said that experience itself
does some days Brandon do you want to
unpack that a little sure so the weight
of an experience I guess imprints
imprints the the neural pathway that
tanya was talking about and then so when
you have a similar experience in the
future there's like a resonance from
that first experience that echoes I
guess it's echo and that's and that's
the voice is that echo of that first
experience bouncing off the the rock
that's now appearing before you that
that's similar to the rock that it came
from okay so the first experience of
inner talk be like nothing's coming up
for me immediately okay good you move
the needle Tanya if you want to follow
follow the rabbit hole yeah sure I I was
feeling into an experience back in my
childhood in elementary school where I
feel like I was developing a sense of
self or identity someone said identity
and there was a context that I was
existing in that had ideas about that
and I also had an experience
that was not necessarily that wasn't
necessarily connected to that
construction or not a product of that
construction but it was interpreted
through that construction and a story
formed about who I was and how the world
is and then that story replicated itself
over and over and over over the years in
different ways in different situations
and burned in a neurological pathway or
pathways yeah so that's a great
explanation of the burning in and I like
this this is a good metaphor for sussing
this out but we're trying to not we're
trying to be very simple which makes it
more difficult okay how does the ability
to talk to yourself get burned in well
through experience but what kind of
experience just the ability to talk to
yourself not the whole experience itself
it's actually very very simple which is
why you can't see it try to think the
source protocol try to think very very
simply
there's a way in which is happening
right now I feel like in relation to you
and the a there are ideas of looking for
the right answer that are creating
static hmm so I'm going to ask you I'm
gonna give you a clue now sometimes
these clothes put you off in the wrong
direction it's not what I'm offering it
for but if it if it goes south I'll just
say forget that clue okay ah okay so
Brandon I think you're onto it but I
want to give the clue for other people
very good work see yeah I think you were
onto it before but you needed your quiet
time wait till I get to it so I want you
to virtualize moving your right hands
raising your right hand don't raise it
just virtualize it in your mind right so
that's a thought what is the fundamental
first experience of raising your right
hand that's not a thought that burns
that into your mind
this isn't easy to be an easy question
but the first experience of raising your
hand yes you raise your hand you burn in
the ability to reimagine it so when you
first learn to raise your hand your
sensory motor practice process is coming
from your core intentional space
activate some motor neurons you burn you
you do this with your hand that pathway
is now accessible for downward causation
which means you can think of raising
your hand so this notion of burning is
perfect now here is the thing about
thought all thought is is the burning of
your mouth moving of your mouth moving
and your ears know when your mouth moves
like this in your tongue that's what it
sounds like it's that's a wavy
fancy-schmancy consciousness thing it's
the subtle recreation of the embodied
experience of talking and hearing burned
in and then down we caused it this is
why Google is creating a sensors that
can read your thoughts because it can
subtly feel the little Tracking's very
subtle movement action patterns that are
sub-threshold when you think inter talk
and that's what it is that's what that
is
does it make sense people don't
especially spiritual people they don't
want to they don't want to know this
because they have a mind-body duality
I think thought is implanted from some
kind of cosmic sphere it's inherently
dialogic in nature it does more it's a
miracle that we can do it it's a miracle
that we can recreate raising your right
hand in your mind right the fact that we
can do that is why you can control an
artificial limb with your mind if you
had never had arms you could not control
artificial limbs because those pathways
the downward causation has not been
burned into your brain and it's not only
your brain many many other things are
involved I just use brain as a
placeholder but inner talk is the same
thing in our talk is the subtle
recreation of sensory motor patterns in
a downward causation
okay yes so but then how can I have an
original thought that we never had
before so let me talk about downward
causation first so downward cop
it's a cybernetics term so in terms of
our burning we mean like when we when we
I'm gonna use vinyl records because I
actually don't know how you make CDs
right so when you're when you're
recording a record first you have the
vinyl and you're burning in the grooves
right that's what we would call upward
causation real experience is setting
pathways so the first time I if I say
water water water water not only is what
I'm getting is I'm getting a covariance
between the what my mouth is doing and
what it sounds like
and so the perceptual sound the
perceptual organs of the ears are
starting to call very with this water
water every time I do this water water
my ears say that feeling of going water
sounds like this and these two things
become coupled that's why I can read
people's lips because I can see what's
happening with their lips feels like
this and then my ears say that's always
coupled with this sound so yeah you know
you're wiring together different aspects
of perception this is why you can teach
mute people to speak by touching when
they touch your face okay so
once were so those get wired together so
this feeling is associated with a sound
we haven't gotten to the meeting yet
symbolic meaning we just talk talking
about the sound and then what happens is
so that's upward causation
now the downward causation is when I am
thinking to say water in my head you can
do it now if you go slow water well and
you're very very aware you can feel that
you feel your mouth doing that
if you exaggerate it and that slight
motor subtle motor pattern your ears are
so primed to say well that's what that
sounds like they add into the
sub-threshold motor movement a sub
threshold sound and that's called sub
vocalization that's called inner talk
so that's what I mean like downward
causation it's not the action the motor
action in the perception you causing an
experience it's activating the patterns
that were burned in to cause the
virtualization of an experience
yes so we're just a thought arise from
weird duck we didn't get there yet but
what if you could and we're not going to
do that today because we're going to we
have to go to symbolic representation
their mental models the structural
architecture of mind and then the
fundamental the fundamental organization
of self other in world
so we already so these are all aspects
of thought we already mentioned some of
the self other in world because we
started by saying you can recreate like
a conversation to people you recreate a
dialogue as' in your brain so so you
that is an organization of self and
other a certain type of organization
itself in other you organize that in
your head and so we have to build up
mind from these different from these
different aspects and inner talk is
actually not a very interesting part of
mine it doesn't give you a lot of
insight it's it uses language which is
coarse-grained right uses language which
is coarse-grained everyone up one of my
first experiences was when I was three
years old and I know I was three years
old because my mother was teaching me
how to pray and I saw I asked her I like
like when did you like teach me how to
pray and she said oh that's when your
sister went to the first grade and so
you were probably three years old I used
to stay home with you and and I know it
was that's how I know it was when I was
three years old and you know we're
Catholics right so you get on your knees
by the side of the bed and you go like
this and you'd say words and I thought
that is weird why would you use words to
talk to God like his words are very
coarse
they seemed like such a crude instrument
too you know anyways so and then then
she said now no and so I said what she
said and then she said and God I'm sorry
that I was mean to my sister and I went
Wow why would you lie to God and I
thought okay well I thought maybe I
thought well you know my mom knows I'm
little and adults have this way of
pretending with kids until they get
older so I just thought well this is
what what one day I would get older and
just this kind of fake way of being
would go away and I remember when I was
about eight or ten or at some point in
my life I realized that they didn't know
even though they were pretending right
so this is how I started my life but but
what I used to do after she we would you
know pretend our prayers I would lay
down
and I would have this practice that I
would call swallowing the words right
because I could see and I try to like
talk to God but swallow the words
because the world word seems like like
always little fault they were always a
little false
they always rang a little false so I
would swallow the words and I'd get
really familiar with how do words come
in your head like where do they come
from him you can find the energy of the
proto world and the energy to articulate
and stuff like that so so these are
discoveries that I've been making by
paying attention for many many years now
and so there's so there's a lot of
neuroscience around this and and really
this is why Google can make this and
face masks with sensors that can read
read your mind because it it
transponders it maje backwards there's a
very subtle sub-threshold motor neurons
in your your speaking area and your
tongue to do exactly what your brain is
doing it's it's it's translating these
submarines or impulses into the expected
perception of sound swallowing words
it's it's so years later I learned that
if you meditate and you want to slow
down monkey mind thoughts in your head
there's a way you know that you can
there's a controlled breathing exercise
and so basically this was what I was
doing was very similar to these tantric
practices so when the words start start
to form
you take a really deep breath and you
pay attention to the really deep breath
and then the the energy that the what
was going to become a word goes away so
I called them swallowing your words
because it had to do with these and you
could get hypertrophic breathing and in
anyways it was just what I would play
around with and I called it swallowing
your words it wasn't sophisticated but
there it's very similar to some
sophisticated techniques you see in
meditation
so let's unmute ourselves and try to
have some some conversation this was you
know around inner talk a question for me
he is where does you know like if
Google's trying to figure out where you
know what's it measuring is it measuring
the thought is measuring the muscles
first you know which comes first but not
because that's so important but where's
this origination of the thought such
that all this stuff can happen yes so
I'll try to get your question but first
I'll make a distinction we're only
talking about inner speech right now
right there's lots of more okay so what
it's a I so if you put sensors on a
person mouth and then you have the the
computer or listening to the words it
makes the AI is doing the same thing
your brain does it's it's recognizing
patterns associated with predictable
sounds right so you just keep running AI
over and over and over again until it
realizes that these patterns may
those sounds so then when you put yeah
right so then if I put this on in it and
I'm thinking words in my mind there's
subtle motor neuron patterns happening
that the AI picks up and then it's and
then it'll you know the the system will
make those sounds for you right yeah
what I'm trying to get to invisible the
where what comes first I mean what where
does this originate from when you have a
sudden thought and some people are
talking about you know imagination
original ideas the impulse for this to
just appear or I mean it feels like it's
really patterned history what I've known
before
okay you know only maybe slight bit of
something new but where where does that
come from that isn't about just the
history and I already recognize and my
previous thoughts and my understanding
of how my thoughts work yeah so some of
it is habit right some of it is the
energy comes up and so it'll come up
into so yeah there's we have to make
distinctions so there's many different
places that can come so for example if
there's an external trigger that is
associated with some kind of emotions
people said this right that you've
wrapped inside a story then you when you
see somebody you might say oh my god
that in your mind it might result in to
mental talk where does it come from when
you bump into a friend on the street
where does all that come from
oh nice days where does that come from
right when we have a certain type of a
certain type of culture we're nervous
and
G is discharged as speech this is our
culture indigenous people they sit for
hours and they'll say second cloud you
know but for us social energy where our
energy energy has to go somewhere it has
to be discharged and for us is just
charged as speech and when there's no
one around
we discharge it as will be speech in
their own head this is what we do
because we have we don't know what else
to do with our energy we have a lot of
nervous energy and this is where it goes
so that's where the impulse one of the
first impulses of inner speech comes
comes to if we're preparing a
presentation of going to an interview
we're not able to be confident that when
the interviewer asked me a question I
just answer the anxiety creates inner
speech and then we prepare or we plant
this and we go through words so that's
one level the energy discharges as in
her speech if you if you have dementia
you actually start talking you know you
walk around and you actually start
talking it doesn't stay sub-threshold
you murmur and talk to yourself if you
have certain types of Tourette syndrome
it doesn't stay sub-threshold okay so
that's one way it's energy discharging
when that's that's who we are as a
culture most Western cultures are like
that it's why we're on zoom' night you
know 24/7 when we're home because we
have all this energy and we just
discharged it on speech this is how we
are as humans and so when we're alone we
discharge it as speech in our head in
many cases it's if you start paying
attention when you start to meditate
your human condition drives you crazy
cuz that's the same thing over
and over and over again your mother your
partner your mother your partner your
mother your kids your partner your
mother your kids right so it doesn't
have it's just it just uses those
patterns that it knows to discharge all
the time
doesn't go anywhere so that's that's one
thing that's and we're talking about
inner talk okay so that's one thing
inter talk can be helpful if you're a
speechwriter and instead of you know
writing down and editing you could lay
down and you could actually go over the
inflection or something in it you know
so you can use it simulating experience
is helpful because you can run a lot
more experiments without using up so
much energy so Nikola Tesla for example
said that he would test his instruments
if he was he would test his inventions
in his head before he actually built
them right so the ability to simulate
experience can be really helpful to ship
his shorthand so that's one thing then
there is we so for example beneath inner
talk is symbolic representation so
that's the meaning of the words and
beneath that are mental models or
stories so we're always trying to
organize their experience in many cases
people get beyond this but in general we
organize our stories our experience in
terms of stories and so even if you're
not hearing your mental talk you have
certain stories like you're the victim
or you're you know the victim of
patriarchy or you're the oppressor or
you're privileged or you're oppressed or
you're so-and-so who's on a career path
or you know we constantly are organizing
experience in these mental models of
self other than world
and where we're at in our history this
is called autobiographical coherence
people most people want autobiographical
coherence once you start to actually be
honest with yourself you see it's just
you're connecting the dots backwards to
make sense of your world and in fact a
person's life doesn't make any sense
you're here for all kinds of reasons
there's no no linear reason but in
general what's very important to people
from a psychic structure is
autobiographical coherence so when
you're when you're this is why it's hard
for us to live in the time of Kovac
because we want to know how does this
fit in this nice little linear
exfoliation right so when we are
disrupted when our autobiographical
coherence is disruptive we retro
actively recreate the story and we often
do that in our head
so we'll say well catch yourself
thinking that so-and-so would never
betray me okay she's my best friend she
would never betray you
and then then something happens and then
you say Shh she wouldn't have betrayed
me if it if her life wasn't so sad now
that you've extended this story so it
still makes sense of the story you have
and sometimes that process you do it by
talking to yourself as your own that
best friend you said why did you do that
what did she tell you settle on another
version of the story and then you live
in that story so that's another way we
could we another time we use internal
talk yeah how do you have agency in
relationship to this mechanism is a
really good question
and one of the things about all of these
about down word causation is
you want to have choice you don't want
it you don't want these scripts to be
running every time the energy comes up
an old script to be running because the
world has changed right
the problem with thought is that it it
relies on downward causation it relies
on something being burned in and then
replayed so it's always behind the
impermanence of the world it's always in
the past right
only the upward causation is an
authentic response to the immediate
present it's always in the past now we
don't you know it's also fun to preserve
memories and to create stories and to
have shared use these imaginatively
in social space you know if you if you
lived with someone for a long time like
me I've been with my partner for like 32
years people come over this Oh tell us
how do you first met and there's always
like there's like a common thread but
always gets embellished with it's no
longer really when we even laugh about
it afterwards it's like yeah that's not
really true anymore to the facts all
these like things about your other life
in what you grown to know about each
other start getting embellished into the
story of how we first met
and now we can't even remember it
anymore
and and so this is downward causation
but this is a fun thing it's it's not a
bad thing but you have agency and
imaginative and it's a work kind of a
work of art in a moment
so one of the things you might be
working with one of the things to work
toward and maybe Kim this is helpful to
you I know I know you're you're you got
some your stuff ins that you want to
figure out is that as you're listening
here and you're trying to figure this
out
which is a good thing you want to go
further we will we'll go further it's
not necessary to turn the energy of
curiosity into inner thought the
thinking process the curiosity itself
can process itself without turning that
into inner thought that's the first step
because inner talk is to coerce an
instrument to work out these very subtle
questions of experience and you get so
you actually live where when you're like
wow that's really interesting you just
still hunt the question I know you took
that course
you don't let the inner top try to work
on it because it's way too coarse an
instrument it's not only to course an
instrument it's like when I was three
years old like why do you use words but
it only has phrases for what's happened
to you in the past because it's a
downward causation so this is why you
don't want to use the words in the
phrase and the thinking process for
discovering something new you want to
feel the energy that curiosity and I'm
gonna use this term for Kim because she
took the course to still hunt it you can
feel it processing there and try and
then you know you might take a look and
use some words and then you'll feel like
you said it just goes around and around
and around I can't get
and then you stop because you haven't
worked it out yeah now this is also very
scientifically valid so I discovered
this in college when I was taking
physics
I had skipped some math courses that I
really should have taken had Advanced
Placement but I really should have taken
them because when it came to do physics
I didn't have enough really
understanding of the math like I
couldn't answer the questions and get
Advanced Placement but it was I was
handicapped because I didn't really have
a good enough understanding of the math
and I would I would be in college just
as before computers you know a long time
ago and I'd be like working on this
problem and this book and I would fall
asleep in the in the we call them
cubicles these little stations and you
know it'd be like 2 o'clock and when I
wake up and then I'd be like oh I know
the answer to that in my sleep
the problem was still working so I
started thinking this was really
interesting so then I started going like
well how long do I work what about any
work for 45 days are the problem we go
back to my room take a nap I started
calling these my elves okay and took me
years or two to find neuroscience or for
neuroscience to discover exactly what's
happening here and so you start to then
go from inner talk to the felt sense you
can really feel the sense that you where
and how your body is working on a
problem and you don't have to pay
attention you get it's like it's gifted
for free and this is actually the way
the child grows the child doesn't work
out how to speak its gifted this for
free the child doesn't you know and this
is how upward causation work
it comes from the inheritance of being a
human and you gifted it for free this is
the abundance of the awakened mind and
the paucity of the monkey mind yeah so
um boy we went through this one fast but
I hope you can see how this is a this
you know and I hope you can play with it
is there any any other questions but and
we're just really here today if he
between today next week if you can
really just pay attention to words in
your head sentences in your head and
maybe if you really pay attention to
them again we're creating a
metacognitive ability to watch the words
in your head then you can start to pay
attention to just before their words in
your head you might get some tension
here sometimes sometimes you might feel
it here you'll start to feel what it
feels like in your body just before the
energy turns into words in your head
when you do that you can work at them
they're at that Junction where people
have done this experiment here and
sometimes people call oh I get them at
the proto thought level now okay then
you're working with just before the
energy turns into two words it's proto
words and then that's a deeper
processing and then you can start to be
actually physically
we're of the sensation of this subtle
processing in which if you try to pay
attention you're just in the way and
then what happens is you start to do
improv insight practice the subtle
processing you don't you go for a walk
you do things they go down to the barn
and I clean up poop and then all of a
sudden when it's ready it's like boom
Wow that's what Whitehead was saying oh
my god Wow
that's what Whitehead was saying and you
start to live from muck up to the
transition from monkey mind to insight
practice insight mind generative mind
this is what we're trying to teach for
collective insight practice is there a
causal link between upward causation and
Boulware yes Dow is not doing is the
sense of the point at which the habits
are not habitual but they're generative
you feel like you're doing nothing
because you're receiving you're
constantly receiving what the body does
now you're not gonna have an insight
you're not going to have an insight Wow
that's what Whitehead was saying if you
didn't do your homework and read
Whitehead and and and give yourself a
lot of tools to process with but once
you've done that you can really you know
you can like I'm doing now I can think
and think I can feel it processing here
and you are free to you need to relax
and you're free to go on walks or enjoy
nature or do chores and then all of a
sudden you'll see something or your
attention will go somewhere and then the
whole insight comes
yes so Ron I don't know if you know me
I'm a big critic of hierarchical
complexity theory development the
hierarchical complexity because it tends
to measure linguistic symbolic
complexity and so they call it the
vertical dimensions and I call this the
depth dimension and it's a different
kind of complexity it's the complexity
of the primitive mind the primitive mind
is more complex and you know more
primitive but more complex than the then
the note went in the modern mind so and
part of this is a bias in our culture
toward what is what is later is always
advanced or progressive it's very hard
for us to do a timeline and see what's
on the far end of the timeline as
regressive I've been Illiad for example
predicted that all all the innovations
in modern life he educated you know he's
the one that said the school's make you
stupid
the medicine makes you sick and the
money makes you poor because he said
that all these advances they level out
and it's like medicine he predicted that
after a certain point and he was writing
in the 70s I think and he said that
point is now all the advances would harm
you maybe all iatrogenic advances and
this has become very obvious in today's
world and so that all these innovations
have have Peaks and then you have to do
something else right and but because we
keep pushing
modern medicine into territories it's
not complex enough to study then after a
certain point all the innovations
and will be harmful and all the things
we teach will still make you stupid and
all the financial instruments we create
will make you poorer because they have
they have a terminus but we under as we
think everything in the future is in
advance so we keep trying to advance
these thick tools that need to be
completely rethought so part of that is
answering Ron's chat question yes so
people that really look at different
hierarchical complexity in those models
in my opinion are looking in the wrong
direction they certainly are true
theories because they described the
modern mind but I don't think they're
describing the emergent mind what we
need I think it's a dead end and we see
this for example and the fact that
postmodern mind is more complex higher
up in the development of hierarchical
complexity but it cannot act it's frozen
it's not a very beneficial mind in many
case it's very reactive and responsive
and deconstructive so some so that
that's part of the sense in which wha
and why I critique those models yeah
that was a good noticing there and of
course all my friends at developmental
psychologists so I have to I'm the thorn
in their sides I
benita I'm reflecting on how this shows
up in my everyday and I've been doing
this liminal space practice at night
where I get rid of all my devices from
my room and I go to sleep and then I
have all this insight in the morning
when I'm waking up and now I'm like how
oh there's all these ways in which I've
been like trying to like this fervent
energy trying to pile on experience
during the day like how many of these
stoah sessions can I do right how many
conversations and so I can like keep you
know and oh like how can I actually do
this allow space to just let my mind do
what it's designed to do over the course
of the day as well and have that little
space practice then yeah you know
sometimes there's rhythms to this and as
a Taoist we say and I think it's really
true Taoism is not sometimes people
think of Taoism this balance in the
sense that you know every day I need
space and rest but it's more like the
you expand your horizon and you see
balance is achieved because sometimes
for like three months you're crazy crazy
doing one thing and then you have three
months of something else right so the
rhythm of this that they're not always
diurnal or you know and you start to
this is something I had to do when I
first left my job in my career in 2012
because I'm we had a small office in a
very big business and you know the work
would just come and come and I really
was very very much enjoyed like just
when I thought I couldn't take anymore
and someone come in a new contract and
and you know get on the phone and get
the trucks and you know it was really
logistical planning and stuff it was fun
you know we built beautiful gardens and
stuff but then all of a sudden I'm home
and I don't have anything coming at me
and the the structure the organism was
completely like lost
really I would I would binge watch Mad
Mad Men yeah Mad Men at night Oh like
for hours because I needed I needed then
I was like an addict to a certain type
of pacing and I knew that's why I was
binge watching it right so and some of
you know rear back she was she said to
me you know a word of wisdom at the
right timing she said it you've spent
your whole career cramming more into
time why don't you why don't you try to
follow the rhythm of time know why don't
you let time lead and figure out what
fits it or something like that you know
it was one of those things she said
beautifully at the time and it didn't
change and then I noticed that I have
rhythms like that and you can trust them
because sometimes you'd be like I'm like
a crazy person in the spring I'm like a
crazy person but the gardens and stuff
but I also have been doing this long
enough to know that I'll be a lazy
person I get in August and then you
start to then let the time shape you
rather you kind of instrumentalizing
time all the time so I wouldn't worry
about it
and then neither worry about a time when
you spend two weeks and you're lazy like
and you'd be like who is this person my
god you know and that's okay too
and then you start to understand that's
a really cool way of understanding this
aspect of experience so you turn time
from a cognitive organizational
principle we'll talk about that too
you're experiencing time for the first
time and it'll be different for everyone
in different
for you at different times in your life
yeah so I don't know if that was helpful
but jump in here for a yeah time to
Earth Hour
so I don't know if you know this Bonita
but Raya is imbedded in their wisdom gym
now so she's coming in at 12 p.m. do a
collective presencing practice you're
the warm-up act for her every Friday is
a good one-two punch so you have people
are interested in this group you can
just go into a store website that CA and
hours before that and I'll just hand it
back to you Bonita just do any closing
thoughts yeah so this was great I hope
it's the right amount of practice and
exercise and talk I always think I talk
a little too much but you know hopefully
you can practice really exploring what
inner talk is and try to find the root
root out of it yeah so breakout groups
would be nice maybe we could do that
next time Peter so that there's more
conversation and more meaning-making
because we will be getting into even it
gets more and more subtle as we explore
the nature of thought and then well if
I'm still around we'll explore the
nature of experience which is even more
subtle and a certain point they blend a
certain point you'll see that a certain
point thought oh is that thought is that
experience and you notice that then
there's a false dichotomy as I started
out with and I just thought if you need
more time maybe 75 minutes or 90 minutes
we can we can do that if if it works
better for them how many sessions if
people have a stomach for word and they
have availability for it I mean I think
this is good but just don't maybe
schedule exactly at the hour because
then I don't want to run into other
people's time okay so there you go this
was hard work
and and I hope you enjoyed it and that
that is actually meaningful and relevant
and I'll see you next week thank you all
so much thank you so much thank you
thank you yeah thank you buddy
that's great